James R. Lilley papers M1849
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
James R. Lilley papers,
1937-2009
M1849
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
11.0 Linear feet (22 manuscript boxes)
This collection contains correspondence, ephemera, newspaper clippings, manuscript drafts and chapter outlines relating to James Lilley’s book China Hands: Nine Decades of Adventure, Espionage, and Diplomacy in Asia. The rest of the collection consists of articles written by James Lilley, United States Department of State Diplomatic Cables, interviews of Lilley, business and personal correspondence (of note are personal letters to, from, and about George Herbert Walker Bush from 1976, 1980, 1993, and 1999), copies of speeches, photographs, newspaper clippings on a variety of subjects, 16 books (including Lilley’s) relating to China’s military and to North Korea, audio visual materials which include VHS tapes of several television interviews of James Lilley, two personal diaries, and photocopies of official United States documents.
Lilley, James R.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Contents
Material was separated into two groups: Papers and Media. A folder listing of the Papers has been made and the material has been re-housed. The Media has been listed individually.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by Sally Lilley to Stanford University, Special Collections in 2011.
Biography
James Roderick Lilley (1928-2009) was an American diplomat who was the ambassador to China during the time of the Tianamen Square protests. The youngest of three children, he was born to American parents in China and was educated in American schools there until he returned to the US in 1940. After graduation from Yale University in 1951, he was employed by the CIA from 1951-1978 and worked in various Asian countries. He served as director of the American Institute in Taiwan from 19981-1984, Ambassador to South Korea from 1986-1989, and Ambassador to China from 1989-1991. He was Assistant Secretay of Defense from 1991-1993, and upon retirement from government service worked at the American Enterprise Institute. His memoir China Hands: nine decades of adventure, espionage, and diplomacy in Asia was published in 2004.
Bush, George, 1924-; Lilley, Sally Booth; Thomas, Lowell; China--Foreign relations--United States; China--Politics and government--1949-; Diplomats--China--Biography.; Diplomats--United States--Biography.; East Asia--Foreign relations--United States; East Asia--Politics and government--1945-; United States--Foreign relations--China; United States--Foreign relations--East Asia
- 1. Papers
  Scope and Contents
  This collection contains correspondence, ephemera, newspaper clippings, manuscript drafts and chapter outlines relating to James Lilley’s book China Hands: Nine Decades of Adventure, Espionage, and Diplomacy in Asia. The rest of the collection consists of articles written by James Lilley, United States Department of State Diplomatic Cables, interviews of Lilley, business and personal correspondence (of note are personal letters to, from, and about George Herbert Walker Bush from 1976, 1980, 1993, and 1999), copies of speeches, photographs, newspaper clippings on a variety of subjects, 16 books (including Lilley’s) relating to China’s military and to North Korea, audio visual materials which include VHS tapes of several television interviews of James Lilley, two personal diaries, and photocopies of official United States documents.
  - Cables C. Peking 89-91 (Box 1, Folders 1-2)
  - June '89 Cables & Documents (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, notes, receipts and other documents relating to: China Hands: Nine Decades of Adventure, Espionage, and Diplomacy in Asia. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wally Booth (Box 1, Folders 6-7)
  - 'China Hands' Letters (Box 2, Folders 1-4)
  - State Dept. Papers (Box 2, Folders 5-6)
  - CIA Material (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - CIA Material (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Discharge Papers (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - James Lilly Bio (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - CRS-Shirley Kan (Box 3, Folders 4-5)
  - Korea (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - De Trani/Korea (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (mainly email) 2005-2009 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bush China Trip 1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Book Letters (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Documents (Expired Identification Cards, Etc.) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Publicity and Performances (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Publicity and Performance (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Speeches (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Exeter-Yale-Jim Tsina Tao (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Lowell Thomas (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Retirement Ceremony 1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Taiwan Media 1982-84 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - James Lilly Personal Correspondence Aug-Dec 1981 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Speeches (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - China Trip 2008 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "Military Power of the People's Republic of China", 2009 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Taiwan-China (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Oklahoma (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - China-U.S. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Taiwan (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Democracy/China (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - China-External (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Chilton/Boulder (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence-1981 (Box 7, Folders 4-5)
  - American Institute In Taiwan - Correspondence and Ephemera (Box 7, Folders 6-7)
  - Special Messages (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - 1973-74 letters (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Personal Correspondence 1984 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Taiwan (Box 8, Folders 2-3)
  - Personal Correspondence 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - James Lilley: Correspondence 2004, 2005 (Box 8, Folders 5-6)
  - James Lilley: Correspondence, 2005 (Box 8, Folders 7-8)
  - China One - 1973 Chapter 10 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Schlesinger Trip 1978 [Nickles/Dawley borrowed 5/18/10] (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Hearst, Nancy: Bio of Han Xu (on CD) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - James Lilley's Diary, China 1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - James Lilley's Diary, China 1973 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - May '89 Documents (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Questions from the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Biographic Summary (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Committee on Foreign Relations April 13, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Life Magazine Image China, circa 1945 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - Clergy - 1989-1990 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Lilley James: Correspondence 1991 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Nomination of Ambassador Lilley (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Beijing 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Congratulations Messages (S. Korea) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Chinese News Clips (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous News Clipping (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Speeches and Notes - Harvard 1991 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Media and Newsclippings, 1990s (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Media and News clippings, 1990s (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Beijing Publicity 1980s and 1990s (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Lilley James: Correspondence 1991 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Communications from U.S. Embassy in Beijing (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Unclassified Memorandum (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - other U.S. Agencies 1989-1990 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Military - 1989-1990 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Leo A. Orleans (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Contacts + Books to read (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Jeff's notes on Frank info (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Guidance (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Childhood in China (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Pyengyang, Korea (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Manuscripts Drafts (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Tientsin (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Battle of Tientsin July-August 1937 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Battle for Shanghai 8137 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Battle of Acking 7-8137 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Interviews (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Post-War Shanghai (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Fall of China '48 Tsing (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Yale recruitment (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Press and news clippings relating to James Lilley, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Bush, George H.W: Correspondence and Ephemera 1970s-1990s (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Bush, George H.W: Correspondence and Ephemera, 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Bush, George H.W: Correspondence and Ephemera 1970s-1990s (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Bush, George H.W: Correspondence and Ephemera 1970s-2009 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Korean War, ROC-PRC friction, Downey (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - State Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - JRL on 1950s Cambodia and Philippines (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Quemoy + Matsu GLF (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Chapter notes and ideas (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Laos -65-68 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Hong Kong 1953 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Hong Kong 68-70 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Washington, Lo-Wn 1970-1973 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - China Articles -70-News-Sun (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - 1975-1981 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - China 73-75 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Taiwan, Politics, Notes on Books (Box 13, Folders 12-14)
  - Arms to Taiwan (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Arms to Taiwan (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Taiwan 82-84 (3/2000 trip interviews) (Box 14, Folders 2-3)
  - North Korea (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - South Korea '86-'88 (Box 14, Folders 5-7)
  - Interviews - China '89-'91 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Rupture (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - China '89-'91 Book notes (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Reconsiliation (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Cable Topics-China '89-'91 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Grane (Epilogue) (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Epilogue: Draft 4 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - OP.ED on China Mention of JRL/Testimony (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Lilley Communication GHWB (41) (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Marketing/Publicity (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Bush 1980 Trip (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Yale-Research (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Chinese Attacks (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Special Quotes and Passages (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and ephemera 2005, 2006 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence and Ephemera 2006-2008 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - U.S. - China Economy: Printed Material 2007, 2008 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Schlesinger Trip Oct./Nov. 1978: Correspondence and Ephemera (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Lilley 1996 Meetings/Conferences on China, Taiwan, and Hong Kong (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Lilley 1996 Meetings/Conferences on Korea (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Lilley 1996 Articles on Korea (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Lilley speeches 1998-2001 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and Ephemera 1996 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Lilley speeches 1996, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Defense Comm. Nat'l Sec. Council (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Tiananmen/China 1989-1991 Letters, articles, and ephemera (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Communication about Book (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Ephemera (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Lilley 1996 articles on China (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Lilley Duplication 2001 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Lilley + Hearings & Testimonies 2001 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Lilley 1996 Testimonies (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Lilley on Hong Kong (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Lilley on Japan (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Notebook undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Box listing (Box 18, Folder 7)
- 2. Media
  Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
  - Special Report w/ Point 6.29.98 (Box 19, Cassette 1)
  - Dereliction of Duty H.R. McMaster (Box 19, Cassette 2)
  - Stef Helper World Wise China 12/17/97 (Box 19, Cassette 3)
  - Governor George W. Bush 1998 GOP Convention Video (Box 19, Cassette 4)
  - China Nuclear Show 10/1/97 NET (Box 19, Cassette 5)
  - LHASA Trip March. April. 1991 Cathy + Mark's tapes. (Box 19, Cassette 6)
  - Playing the China Card "Nixon & Mao" & "The Tiananmen Hostage" VHS NTSC (Box 19, Cassette 7)
  - James Lilley 05/21/07 (Box 19, Cassette 8)
  - Crossfire 3/9/99 (Box 19, Cassette 9)
  - 20010322 Slug: US - Lilley (Box 19, Cassette 11)
  - With the Compliments of Benjamin Lu Representative Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office in the United States (Box 20, Cassette 2)
  - Larry King Live 4/11/2001 Ambassador James Lilly (Box 20, Cassette 1)
  - Fox TV PRC White Paper 22 2000 (Box 19, Cassette 10)
  - CNN Business Asia (Box 20, Cassette 3)
  - J. Lilly CNN (Box 20, Cassette 4)
  - "China Now" Promo Tape TRT: 7 Minutes 02/17/95 (Box 20, Cassette 5)
  - Great Decisions 1995 Show #706 China, Taiwan, Hong Kong 02/06/95 TRT: 28:15 (Box 20, Cassette 6)
  - Oregon State of Wonder (Box 20, Cassette 7)
  - Yes, Taiwan Does Exist. (Box 20, Cassette 8)
  - Ambassador Lilly "Korean Situation" (Box 20, Cassette 9)
  - Litasa, Tibet March-Apr 1991 (Box 20, Cassette 10)
  - EW 02.12.95 (Box 21, Cassette 1)
  - Lockout: The Case of Taiwan and the UN (Box 21, Cassette 2)
  - The Death of Yugoslavia - BBC TX Programme 1: "Enter Nationalism" & 2: "The Road to War" (Box 21, Cassette 3)
  - Korea (Box 21, Cassette 4)
  - Charlie Rose: JAmes Lilley - 4/3/01 (Box 21, Cassette 5)
  - WNT Dub Sements from 4/2/01 (Box 21, Cassette 6)
  - [unlabeled cassette] (Box 21, Cassette 7)
  - Downey/Fecteau/Award Ceremony 6/25/98 (Box 21, Cassette 8)
  - A Celebration of 50 Years of China Operations Stanley Bergman (Box 21, Cassette 9)
  - America's Voice Tonight 4 May '98 (Box 21, Cassette 10)
  - 7/29/99 VOA (Box 21, Cassette 11)
  - Unlabeled Cassette (Box 22, Cassette 1)
  - Unlabeled Cassette (Box 22, Cassette 2)
  - China: Opening the Door to the East (Box 22, Cassette 3)
  - "The Hazelden Experience" (Box 22, Cassette 4)
  - Japan NHK aired a 8 April 2001 (Box 22, Cassette 5)
  - CNN/ Nick Platt/J. Lilley (Box 22, Cassette 6)
  - The Leadership Institute presents From Dream to Reality (Box 22, Cassette 7)
  - 12:00 - 17:00 (Box 22, Cassette 8)
  - Kathrine Baumann Beverly Hills (Box 22, Cassette 9)
  - [Empty Cassette Case] (Box 22, Cassette 10)
  - Swearing-in Ceremony, China, 24 April '89 (Box 22, Cassette 11)
  - 8/22/89 AMB Lilley W/ D. Trout/ABC (Box 22, Cassette 12)
  - Kimjongilia (Box 22, Compact disc 13)